Guide to the Phil Teigen North American churches postcard collection, 1904-2010
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections Research Center.
Phil Teigen North American churches postcard collection
1904-2010
C0317
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections Research Center.
3.0 linear ft.
This collection contains postcards of churches of many Christian denominations from the United States and Canada.
Teigen, Philip M., 9999-9999
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Phil Teigen on 9/11/2018.
Historical note
Immigrants from Europe and Asia brought a wide variety of Christian beliefs to North America. As Peter Williams notes, "The pluralism of America's religious experience is a given from the beginnings, first for the colonial settlements in aggregate, then later in virtually every town, city, and state" ("Houses of God", xii). He goes on to describe how these many religious groups impacted the built environment as they came "in succeeding waves of immigration, each bringing with them and/or adapting for their own purposes a wide variety of types of houses of worship and other sacred sites and structures" ("Houses of God," xii). This diversity of religious architecture is reflected in material commemorative culture, including through postcards.
Scope and Content note
This collection contains postcards from churches of many denominations across the United States and Canada. The postcards date from 1904-2010, although many are undated. The processor included undated in the date range for a series or box if it seemed likely that some of the postcards in the group date from outside the given range. More than half of the postcards depict Lutheran churches; there are also many postcards of Roman Catholic churches and Episcopal churches, as well as other Christian denominations. The postcards are organized by denomination and alphabetically by state (sometimes city), as well as whether they depict church interiors or exteriors.
Series 1: Lutheran churches, 1904-2010 (Boxes 1-7) includes postcards of Lutheran churches from the United States and Canada. It is divided into two subseries, Lutheran church exteriors and Lutheran church interiors.
Series 2: Roman Catholic churches, 1907-1995 (Boxes 8-10) includes postcards of Roman Catholic churches across the United States and Canada.
Series 3: Episcopal churches, 1908-1983, undated (Boxes 10-11) includes postcards of Episcopal churches across the United States and Canada.
Series 4: Other denominations, 1908-2000 (Boxes 11-12) is the smallest series, and includes postcards of a variety of churches, including Methodist, Presbyterian, Baptist, Orthodox, and other denominations, as well as non-denominational.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into four series by denomination. Within Series 1-3, postcards are organized alphabetically by state or province.
Series 1: Lutheran churches, 1904-1910 (Boxes 1-7)
Series 2: Roman Catholic churches, 1907-1995 (Boxes 8-10)
Series 3: Episcopal churches, 1908-1983, undated (Boxes 10-11)
Series 4: Other denominations, 1908-2000 (Boxes 11-12)
Related Material
The Special Collections Research Center also holds the, which contains postcards from a German World War I medic.
Bibliography
Williams, Peter W. "Houses of God: Region, Religion, and Architecture in the United States." Urbana/Chicago: University of Illinois Press, 1997.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Catholic church buildings.; Church buildings.; Lutheran church buildings
Document Types:
Postcards.
Contents List
A detailed inventory of individual postcards in the collection can be found here:
- Series 1: Lutheran churches, 1904-2010 (Boxes 1-7)
  Scope and Content
  This series contains postcards of Lutheran churches. It is divided into two subseries: Lutheran church exteriors and Lutheran church interiors.
  - Subseries 1.1: Lutheran church exteriors, 1904-2010
    - Alabama-Indiana, 1905-2001 (Box 1)
    - Iowa-Minnesota, 1904-1988 (Box 2)
    - Minnesota, 1907-1986 (Box 3)
    - Mississippi-Ohio, 1906-1977, undated (Box 4)
    - Ohio-South Carolina, 1905-2010 (Box 5)
    - South Dakota-Wisconsin, 1906-1999 (Box 6)
    - Wisconsin-Wyoming, 1907-1967, undated (Box 7)
  - Subseries 1.2: Lutheran church interiors, 1906-2000
    - Alabama-Wisconsin, 1906-2000 (Box 7)
- Series 2: Roman Catholic churches, 1907-1995 (Boxes 8-10)
  This series includes postcards of Roman Catholic churches across the United States and Canada.
  - Alabama-Massachusetts, 1907-1986 (Box 8)
    Also includes unknown at beginning
  - Michigan-Pennsylvania, 1907-1989 (Box 9)
  - Prince Edward Island - Wyoming, 1907-1995 (Box 10)
- Series 3: Episcopal churches, 1908-1983, undated (Boxes 10-11)
  This series includes postcards of Episcopal churches across the United States and Canada.
  - Alabama-New York, 1908-1983, undated (Box 10)
  - North Carolina-Wyoming, 1910-1976, undated (Box 11)
- Series 4: Other denominations, 1908-2000 (Boxes 11-12)
  This is the smallest series, and includes postcards of a variety of churches, including Methodist, Presbyterian, Baptist, Orthodox, and other denominations, as well as non-denominational.
  - African Methodist Episcopal churches, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 11)
  - Baptist churches, 1953-1983, undated (Box 11)
  - Churches of the Brethren, circa 1950s-1983 (Box 11)
  - Christian churches, 1957-1977, undated (Box 11)
  - Christian Science churches, 1934-1962 (Box 11)
  - College and university non-denominational churches, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 11)
  - Community churches, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 11)
  - Congregational churches, 1908-1986 (Box 11)
  - Evangelical and Reformed churches, 1910-1974, undated (Box 11)
  - Mennonite churches, 1964 (Box 11)
  - Methodist churches - Alabama-Missouri, 1920-1990 (Box 11)
  - Methodist churches - Montana-Wyoming, 1908-circa 1970s, undated (Box 12)
  - Military churches, 1953-1977, undated (Box 12)
  - Assemblies of God, Nazarene, Moravian, etc. churches, 1952-1954, undated (Box 12)
  - Non-denominational churches, 1908-1990 (Box 12)
  - Orthodox churches, 1959-1973, undated (Box 12)
  - Presbyterian churches, 1908-2000 (Box 12)
  - Unitarian/Universalist churches, 1936-1970, undated (Box 12)
  - United Church of Christ, 1956-1992, undated (Box 12)